The Samuel Coleridge-Taylor Collection
Yale University Music Library
The Samuel Coleridge-Taylor Collection
1899-1912
Misc. Ms. 290
Yale University Music Library
1.5
(2 boxes)
Music and correspondence by the African-English composer Samuel Coleridge-Taylor (1876-1912)
Coleridge-Taylor, Samuel, 1875-1912
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Arrangement
In 2 series as follows: I. Music by Coleridge-Taylor. II. Correspondence.
Scope and Contents
The Samuel Coleridge-Taylor Collection consists of scores and/or parts to 4 of Coleridge-Taylor's musical compositions and extracts of 2 letters from Coleridge-Taylor to Carl Stoeckel.
Biographical / Historical
Samuel Coleridge-Taylor was born in London on August 15, 1875 to African and English parents. He studied composition (with Charles Villiers Stanford) and violin at the Royal Conservatory of Music. After completing his studies in 1897, he held a variety of posts as a conductor and teacher, while pursuing a career as a composer. The best known of his many works is the cantata Hiawatha's Wedding Feast. Coleridge-Taylor's growing international fame took him to the United States three times, and he composed The Bamboula for the Norfolk Music Festival in Norfolk, Connecticut in 1910. (The present collection is a product of that visit. The Stoeckel Family Papers contain additional pertinent information.) Samuel Coleridge-Taylor died in Croydon, England on September 1, 1912; he was only 37 years old.
Cantatas, Secular -- Parts; Composers -- Correspondence; Orchestral music -- Scores and parts; Coleridge-Taylor, Samuel, 1875-1912; Stoeckel, Carl, 1858-1925
- Register (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Music by Coleridge-Taylor, Series I
  - [Bamboula] The bamboula: rhapsodic dance / by S. Coleridge Taylor. -- London: Hawkes & Son; New York: J.W. Stern, c1911, 1 score (51 p.); 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    General
    For orchestra.
    "To Mr. & Mrs. Carl Stoeckel."
    2 copies.
    Pl. no.: H. & S. 4728
  - [Bamboula] The bamboula: rhapsodic dance / by S. Coleridge-Taylor. -- London: Hawkes & Son: New York: J.W. Stern, c1912, 110 parts; 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    For picc/flI-II/obI-II/clI-II/bnI-II/hnI-IV/ tptI-II/tbnI-III/tuba/tp/perc/vlnI/vln II/vla/vc/db.
    Program note on cover of vln I part.
  - [Death of Minnehaha] The death of Minnehaha: a cantata, op. 30, no. 2 / composed by S. Coleridge-Taylor. -- London: Novello, [1899], 41 parts; 37 cm. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Parts for: picc/flI-II/obI-II/clI-II/bnI-II/hnI-IV/cornetI-II/tptI-II/ tbnI-III/tuba/tp/perc/harp/vlnI/vlnII/vla/vc/db.
    Lacks vocal parts.
    Pl. no.: 10970.
  - [Hiawatha's wedding-feast] Hiawatha's wedding-feast, op. 30 / composed by S. Coleridge-Taylor. -- London: Novello; New York: Novello, Ewer, [1898], 42 parts; 37 cm. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Parts for: picc/flI-II/obI-II/clI-II/bnI-II/hnI-IV/cornetI-II/ tptl-II/tbnI-III/tuba/tp/perc/harp/vlnI/vlnII/vla/vc/db.
    Pl. no. 10755
  - [Keep me from sinkin' down] Keep me from sinkin' down / by S. Coleridge-Taylor, 32 manuscript parts; 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Copyist's manuscript in ink.
    For flI-II/obI-II/clI-II/bnI-II/hnI-II/tp/solo vln/vlnI/vlnII/vla/vc/db.
    Corrections in pencil.
    Typed on caption: "Property of Carl Stoeckel."
- Correspondence, Series II
  - Carl Stoeckel to Samuel Coleridge-Taylor, December 23, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Photocopied extract.
  - Carl Stoeckel to Samuel Coleridge-Taylor, January 31, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 8)